[SPEAKER_01]: It's only about... you say something about contentment with the basic requisites.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's something that most people would like to have, if they thought about it, to be satisfied with that which is available, readily available to you, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, good enough food, good enough clothing, good enough shelter and enough medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's... even though we have those things available... People want more.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no contentment, generally.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no contentment because there is no... because people are careless in regard to their desires.
[SPEAKER_02]: Contentment requires maintenance.
[SPEAKER_02]: It requires you to... to foresee things before they arise, to foresee a possibility for proliferation before it arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just... obviously, there's everything else that you... if somebody's just starting, it's going to be unpleasant because of the discomfort and it's going to... it's going to require some doing and learning.
[SPEAKER_02]: But once a person develops that habit, then, yeah, they don't need to be constantly obsessing over simplicity and keeping things simple and requisites, because that would become the way they prefer to live.
[SPEAKER_02]: But until they reach that point, you do need to keep yourself in check.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's pretty much it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just ask yourself, well, hold on, do I need this much?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or do I need this many?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can I... is this sufficient?
[SPEAKER_02]: And most often the answer is yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the reason why people always go for more is because of the unquestioned attitude towards avoiding discomfort.
[SPEAKER_02]: People don't want discomfort.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, do I need a mattress of that thickness?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, you know, if I don't... if I don't have it sufficiently comfortable, I won't sleep at night.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you might not sleep first night or second night.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where third night, you'll be so tired, you'll sleep on a concrete block.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you train yourself in that regard.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, you don't have to... you don't have to do it, sort of, without a purpose, as in just... just try to renounce everything and... and... and not eat and sleep on a stone.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you know, if that brings the unwholesome states to decrease and wholesome states to increase, yeah, by all means.
[SPEAKER_02]: But doing it in itself, because sometimes people can get intoxicated with that sort of the taṅga,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you always want to keep it practical.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you know you won't be able to kind of veer off too far
[SPEAKER_02]: Into conceited determination of I'm the best, I'm the toughest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Keep it practical.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like things that are genuinely practical.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things that are not necessary, that can then support your practice towards wakefulness and towards diminishing of the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, the little things.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to throw everything away, but yeah, ask yourself, is my mattress too soft?
[SPEAKER_02]: Could I sleep on a harder surface?
[SPEAKER_02]: What would the result be?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it would be less sleep, because you wouldn't be able to overly enjoy it, because it's not too comfortable, which means, okay, so that could bring the unwholesome states to decrease and wholesome states to increase.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means I won't be indulging in the sleep.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you remove your mattress and sleep on a wooden board.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're doing it out of some sort of self-advertisement, well...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it can still arise, it can still be made wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in a way, it's still... it's still okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, eh... it's important to distinguish the two.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether it's done out of just some sort of inspirational determination, or if it's done for the purpose of practically supporting your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, becoming stronger, being able to... Yeah, tougher.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can take more then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means you'll be bothered less, because you can take more.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you can take physical pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Take more by taking less.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But yeah, if your body is dependent on a certain amount of comfort, well, you would struggle.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were to leave the softness of your home, your environment, your bedroom, you would struggle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, ask yourself, like, is my current situation really making me tougher and able to endure the elements?
[SPEAKER_02]: As the Buddha said, that you should.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, some of the taints are to be abandoned by enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, you can ask yourself, honestly, then, well, would I be abandoning any of those things if I can't even give up my five-inch mattress?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, you're supposed to be enduring cold and heat and mosquitoes and insects, discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or just an evening meal, eating, eating less, those people.
[SPEAKER_02]: True, true, eating less, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it necessary?
[SPEAKER_02]: Will I, will I die if I don't eat until tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_02]: Will this hunger kill me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I genuinely, like, fainting and, I don't know, losing my senses?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just a bit of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's also in terms of shelter, you know, trying to get your surroundings, in terms of your shelter, perfectly spiritual, in a way, so that you can practice correctly, so that you can become a stronger person.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, that's all rooted in that, as I said, misguided inspiration and determination.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's more on a level of people's identity and what they do and what they're practicing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not really rooted properly on the level of actually trying to uproot the identity, belongings, appropriation, sense of self, life and existence.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, people have a little shrine and they have a little setup.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, again, we have to differentiate.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're talking about a casual lay person who is practicing, or you're talking about somebody who is really sort of going for it, committed to it full-on.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're just doing it part-time, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: These little reminders can be helpful, because, well, yeah, you're not giving up the life.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're actually a monk or something like that, then, yeah, it's not really
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, a monk who is practicing towards arahantship or towards understanding the dhamma, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because shrines can be focuses of your intention to practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well... not really.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, again, as I said, if you live a busy lay life and you have no intention of leaving it, then, yeah, a little shrine can remind you of certain values.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, the Buddha said, yeah, like, you know, if you're not doing anything else, go and visit the place with the target that was born and so on, because it will make you think about him, as in think about the values of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_02]: But having a shrine, a worshipping shrine, for the sake of your practice, well, it's just completely redundant.
[SPEAKER_02]: It makes no difference, literally.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's neither contributing... Well, it could be taking away, if you think that's what practice is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I think most people don't think that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might do it out of a habit or some sort of like pleasing identity.
[SPEAKER_02]: My shrine, my ajahn, my this, my that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is fine, but if you want to arrive at any relevant distinction, that needs to be overcome.